<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spirituall snapsacke for the Parliament souldiers. Containing cordiall encouragements, effectuall perswasions, and hopefull directions, unto the successefull prosecution of this present cause. by J. P.</title>
            <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E103_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17482</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860202</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90971)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E103[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spirituall snapsacke for the Parliament souldiers. Containing cordiall encouragements, effectuall perswasions, and hopefull directions, unto the successefull prosecution of this present cause. by J. P.</title>
                  <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Overton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the Yeare, 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May.24.".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Roundheads --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155919:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Spirituall SNAPSACKE <hi>FOR THE</hi> PARLIAMENT SOVLDIERS CONTAINING, Cordiall Encouragements, Effectuall Perſwaſions, and hopefull Directions, unto the Succeſſefull proſecution of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent CAUSE.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> in the Yeare,
1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:155919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155919:2"/>
            <head>To His Excellence ROBERT EARLE OF ESSEX; Viſcount
<hi>Hereford,</hi> Baron <hi>Ferrars</hi> of <hi>Chart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> Lord
<hi>Bourcheir</hi> and <hi>Lovaine,</hi> One of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councell, and Generall of the Army raiſed by the Parliament, in Defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, his Majeſties Perſon, the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdome, and the Priviledges of
<hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reatneſſe and Goodneſſe as they are infinitely in GOD, ſo in what degree they concentre in Man, they have a God like Divine influence and power to create Love, and Reſpect Boldneſſe and Reverence in Perſons Inferior; Your goodneſſe hath made you Great, and your Greatnes (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to common Experience) hath made you Good; and both theſe hath emboldened me humbly to ſolicite your <hi>Excellence,</hi> that this ſmall <hi>Snapſacke,</hi> upon the ſtricteſt ſearch of your dilligent Sentinels, and approbation thereof, may freely paſſe among your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers: It is not my preſumption to preſent your <hi>Excellence,</hi> with the broken Morſells Cram'd up therein, knowing that Curious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155919:3"/>Carving fit for ſuch a perſonage, becomes not a <hi>Snap ſacke;</hi> and well Conſidering, both your plentifull Supply from your Spirituall Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, and mine owne inſufficiency, being neither a Prophet, nor a Prophets Sonne: but the beſt of my hopes, is your
<hi>EXCELLENCIES</hi> permiſsion of its free Portage; and could it procure the light of your countenance, and your Command of it's uſe as a taken hereof it would be to its Author like the <hi>filling of the poore Widdowes Veſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls for the Oyle in the Cruce, a greater</hi> reward, then ever
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s look't for: howſoever, the Eternall God, and our ſucceeding Poſterity ſhall call you bleſſed for your Love, Zeale, and Courage, in Gods and your Countries Cauſe: And that the Almighty may not onely make you a <hi>Moſes, to lead his</hi> Iſrael
<hi>out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and bring you to Mount</hi> Nebo <hi>in the ſight of the good Land;</hi> But a <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to bring them into the Poſſeſsion thereof, removing all Obſtacles, ſupplying all wants, in your way; fill you withall the divine qualifications of the worthies of Iſrael; <hi>make you Strong and of good Courage, bee with you, never leave you nor forſake you,</hi> is the earneſt Prayer, as of many thouſands the Iſraelites of GOD, ſo amongſt them, of your <hi>EXCELLENCIES</hi> moſt humbly Devoted, Vnworthy, whoſe Name ſhould be Spel'd out,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155919:3"/>
            <head>A SPIRITVALL SNAPSACKE FOR THE PARLIAMENT SOVLDIERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AN is borne to ſorrow, becauſe borne in ſinne, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible ſecurity is his chiefeſt miſery; common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and common Saylors are moſt commonly under the ſhadow of death, and ſeldome mindefull of another life; the conſideration whereof, is the ground of our preſent diſcourſe; wherein as brevitie muſt be our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; becauſe many morſells muſt be cram'd up in a ſmall Snapſack; ſo ſpiritualitie muſt be our Subject for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Souldiers for whom this is chiefly intended, have a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Palate, the bread of life is their Hony-comb, and Angells food their fare, Gods word is their delight, and all their well Springs are therein, (a rare thing in common Souldiers.)</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe they cannot come to the common Markets where this Proviſion is to be had, this is their ſorrow, but not their ſinne; Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are rarely in the Souldiers march, and therefore a little in the Snap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack will doe ſome good, for <hi>to the hungry ſtomack every bitter thing is ſweet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, through conſtant want of wholſome dyet, corrupt food may doe ſome hurt, I meane the body of ſinne within; and evill Company without, proves bitter to an honeſt minde, to <hi>dwell in Kedar is his woe,</hi> and <hi>to march in Meſech his complaint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe they are ſubject to many ſorrowes, for
<hi>good Souldiers muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155919:4"/>endure hardneſſe,</hi> cold and hunger; Wounds and Soares are commonly the Souldiers ſhare, ſpirituall refection will beare them up, the waters of Life proves Cordiall in fainting fits, and in outward troubles inward comfort refreſheth the minde.</p>
            <p>But leaſt we ſhould be longer in untying the ſtrings; then your ſtomacks will beare (being ſharp ſet) roule theſe conſiderations, as ſo many ſweet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells under your tongue, to beare up your hearts in your hardeſt worke)</p>
            <p>Firſt you HAVE A GOOD CAUSE (a ſingular incouragement to a pious minde) amongſt all other cauſes that ever drew Armies into the field, yours for goodneſſe hath the precedencie; and this will appeare by theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is a moſt <hi>cleare and candid cauſe,</hi> whoſe ſhining beauty and refined perſpicuity amongſt all other cauſes, is like the Sunne in the Firmament. It is not my purpoſe to anſwer ſcruples about the cleareneſſe of the Cauſe, they for whom this is provided, are not to ſeeke in this particular, the Swords in their hands argues the cleareneſſe of their Judgements herein, neither are they ſingular in this opinion; all the Godly, Learned, and conſcientious Miniſters, and people of the Kingdome will joyne iſſue with them herein; ſatisfaction herein from learned Orthodoxe, and godly Divines in this particular hath bin like the
<hi>waters of Iordan in the time of harveſt:</hi> witneſſe,
<hi>Goodwins</hi> Anticaval: ſeverall Anſwers to Dr. <hi>Fearne,</hi> a late Treatiſe made by many Godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in juſtification of Defenſive Armes, and few there are of the contrary judgement, but Papiſts, Athieſts, Praelates, Delinquents, and prophane wretches (excepting ſuch who may exchange their eye-ſight with <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe) and cannot ſee the drawne ſword of ruine or ſlavery in their baſe ſubmiſſion to the adverſe party.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the Cauſe is <hi>cleare,</hi> ſo it is A MOST FULL AND GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RALL CAUSE, ſoule and body in all their preſent concernments are deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſſed in the ſame.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Firſt for Matters of the Soule conſider:</head>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>you fight for God,</hi> who will therefore fight for you, <hi>the Battell is his,</hi> the Victory therefore ſhall be yours,
<hi>mighty in Battell</hi> is God for you, Couragious in Battell be you for Him, you fight for Him; whoſe glorious Attributes will be unto you a
<hi>munition of Rocks.</hi> 33. <hi>Eſay</hi> 16. You fight for Him whoſe glorious name will be unto you a ſtrong Tower, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. You fight for Him, at whoſe Command is Heaven and Earth for your defence; you fight for Him who hath divided the Seas for paſſage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.21. ſmitten Rocks for drinke, <hi>Ex dus</hi> 17.6. given Angells food for meat.
<hi>Exod.</hi> 16.14. Who hath made the Mountaines to skip like Rams and the little Hills like Lambs, 114. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. Who hath bound Kings in chaines and Nobles in Fetters of Iron. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8. Who hath rebuked Kings and deſtroyed mighty Princes in the behalf of thoſe that fought for him; you fight for Him in whoſe hands is the breath of your noſtrills and all your wayes, &amp; without whoſe Providence not one hair of your head ſhall fall to the ground; Who can protect in Battells, ſucceed Battells, reſtore loſſes, make up breaches, and give you an inheritance and Crowne with glory, who would not fight for ſuch a God?</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:155919:4"/>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>you fight for Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath fought with Heaven and Earth, and Hell for you, who became <hi>ſinne</hi> to make you <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> to make you a
<hi>bleſsing;</hi> who gave Glory for ſhame, Life for death Joy for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that you may exchange ſhame for Glory; death for Life; and ſorrow for Joy; broken for your ſinnes was hee, that your breaches may be made up, cruſht was Ieſus Chriſt for you, that you might once be crowned with him; you fight for that Jeſus which is the God of Glory the Lord of Hoaſts the Head of Angells, the Heir of Heaven, the Prince of Peace, whoſe everlaſting thoughts eternall purpoſes, timely actions, moſt bitter paſſions, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worke at the throne of Grace, whoſe all in all, was and is and ever ſhall be, for your preſent and eternall good; and who would not fight for ſuch a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>you fight for the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> his worke in the World in the hearts of the Saints, is the great Controverſie between you and your Adverſaries. God in you is their malice againſt you, you fight for that ſpirit that fills you with joy unſpeakeable, and full of Glory: by which you are ſealed to the day of Redemption, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. by which you are comforted in all your tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. which maketh you meete for the inheritance with the Saints in light, 1 <hi>Col.</hi>
12. which <hi>ſtayeth you with Flagons, and comforteth you with Apples,</hi>
2 <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. affording ſuch meat which the World knowes not of, which hall be as Rivers of water in a dry place, and as the ſhadow of a mighty Rock in a weary Land, whoſe inward heat of life and joy ſhall (like the fire in the Temple) never be extinct.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, you fight for the glorious Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, and the through-fare thereof in your Native Country: that Goſpell that hath brought life and immortalitie to light, which hath diſcovered bowells of Grace in God to you from all eternity, the treaſure of Comfort, the viſion of Heaven, the ſupport of Saints, the rule of life, the way of Peace, the path to Glory.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, you fight for Sion and all her priviledges, for Sion and her Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, for Sion and her children, for Sion, the houſe of God, 76.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. the Arke of God, the Temple of God, the joy of God, 132.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 13. the perfection of beautie, 50. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. for Sion the Subject of Gods love, 87. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. of his deſire, 132.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. of his Jelouſie, 8 <hi>Zachary</hi> 2. the friend, the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the Spouſe of Chriſt, for Sion which whoſoever hateth ſhall be turned backward 129. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. to favour whoſe duſt is an acceptable ſervice in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the fulneſſe and generality of the Cauſe, in reſpect of the ſoule, you fight for the God of Grace, for Jeſus Chriſt the gift of Grace, the ſpirit of Grace; the Goſpell of Grace and the children of Grace.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſee the fulneſſe of the Cauſe in reſpect of the outward man, in many particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you fight for your King (though this be eſteemed a Paradox, a Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, a lye, a ſcorne, becauſe it is contrary to his Commands, and his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is with thoſe againſt whom you fight, and ſo in danger) yet firſt you take up Armes in, under, and for the defence of his lawfull Authority ſetled in Parliament, and not among Cavaliers, againſt thoſe whoſe endeavours are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155919:5"/>to deſtroy the Parliament, and Lawes of the Land, and conſequently all his Royall and lawfull authority, and ſo either to unking and dethrone him, or make him a Tyrant, the high way to ruine him, by expoſing him to the wrath of God, and the dangerous hazards of a Tyrannicall Government, which are commonly ſtabs, poyſon, plers, and Treaſons.</p>
               <p>You fight for his Authority which is greater then his
<hi>perſonall Commands,</hi> if he ſhould perſonally edmmand to murther, which is forbidden by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie; which would be moſt diſloyall; he that diſobeyeth the one, or the other? the King ſaith he will rule us by
<hi>Law;</hi> and make his <hi>will</hi> that Law, though it be in things contrary to <hi>knowne Lawes,</hi> and you fight againſt his <hi>will,</hi> becauſe contrary to his <hi>Authority,</hi> which is greater than his
<hi>Will;</hi> the party you fight againſt reſiſt his lawfull
<hi>Authoritie,</hi> you his <hi>corrupt Will,</hi> they his <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> you his <hi>Command,</hi> they withſtand him as a King, you as a
<hi>man,</hi> who are the greater Rebells? his <hi>deliberate Will</hi> is in
<hi>Parliament,</hi> ſignified by his <hi>Writ,</hi> and <hi>Act of continuance,</hi> his <hi>paſsionate will</hi> is in his <hi>Camp</hi> ſignified by his Commands, that you ſhould not obey <hi>his will</hi> in Parliament, what will you doe? you will ſay he is not preſent in Parliament, therefore the third Eſtate which is eſſentiall thereunto is gone and, ſo there is a diffolution of the whole. I anſwer his
<hi>power</hi> is there though not his <hi>Perſon,</hi> he is not in his inforiour Courts perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, but vertually, and ſo he is in Parliament his
<hi>Perſon</hi> may die, but not his <hi>power,</hi> you are proclaimed Traitors by his <hi>mouth,</hi> your Enemies by his <hi>Law,</hi> you by his
<hi>Perſon,</hi> they by his <hi>power,</hi> you are proclaimed Traitors, but what is the Treaſon? you will not quietly let your throats be cut, nor ſuffer the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be deſtroyed, you will not advance Prerogative above Law, nor permit an Army of Theives to take away all you have without reſiſtance, you will not deſtroy the Kings lawfull Authority by ſubmitting your ſelves to his unlawfull Commands; you will not permit curſed men to deſtroy the Parliament as <hi>Doog</hi> at <hi>Sauls</hi> tyrannicall command, did deſtroy the Lords Prieſts, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22 18 but defend them from ſlaughter, as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Abiathar</hi> v.
23. in a word, you will not be made ſlaves, but ſay you are free borne, and this is Treaſon, how prove you that? why your <hi>Enemies</hi> call it ſo?</p>
               <p n="2">2. You fight for the recovery of his Royall Perſon out of the hands of thoſe miſcreants, and reinſtate Him in his Royall Throne and Dignity, that both He and his Poſteritie (if God will) may yet flouriſh in their Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, ſo that notwithſtanding all contradictions you fight for your King.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you fight for your Countrie, for the peace of it againſt the great diſturbers thereof. 2. For the plentie of it againſt the Plunderers, tobbers, ſpoylers, deſtroyers thereof. 3. For the Libertie of it, the Lawes power and Priviledges thereof in Parl our Nationall Inheritance. 4. For all your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſts in any thing you enjoy, your Houſes, Lands, Eſtates, Callings, what ever you have is loſt if the day be loſt. 5. You fight for your neereſt relations, your Wives and poore children who are undone; if you give up the Cauſe: if the Principles of Heathens have rendered them valiant for their Countries good, and their Valour famous to ſucceeding poſteritie; ſhall not the Principles of piety be ſtronger in Chriſtians? thus you have a good cauſe, it is clearely good, it is fully good, for God, your King, your Countrey, in all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155919:5"/>their references, never the like cauſe (all things conſidered) from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World untill this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Secondly, as you have a good Cauſe; ſo conſider WHAT A LIFE GUARD God hath ſet about you for your ſecurity.</head>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>God himſelfe is your Life guard,</hi> 52. Eſay
12. <hi>the Lord ſhall goe before you, and the God of Iſraell ſhall be your Reereward,</hi> there is God in Front and Reare, he ſhall be unto you a munition of Rocks, 33. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 15.16. <hi>He that walketh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly &amp;c. he ſhall dwell en high, his place of Defence ſhall be a munition of Rocks,</hi> and the Church is ſaid <hi>to dwell in the clefts of the Rocks,</hi> 2 Canticles 14 and <hi>the name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower</hi> Prov. 18.10. a little Sauctuary will God be unto you, 11.
<hi>Ezekiell</hi> 16. He will be a ſhield, a buckler, a ſtrong Tower, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, a Defence, againſt the terrour of the night, the arrow or bullet that flieth in the day: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.5. what though <hi>Ammon and Geball, Edom and Iſhmaell, Moaband the Agarims, what though Amaleck and the Philiſtims, Aſhur and the Children of Lot;</hi> though Papiſts and Atheiſts, and all their Allyes though France and Spaine, though Turke and Pope, though all the World ſhould <hi>compaſſe you about like Bees;</hi> yet <hi>if the Lord be your ſtrength and refuge, he will become your ſong and your ſalvation,</hi> Pſal. 118.12. was not God thus unto you at
<hi>Keynem</hi> Battell? to the amazement of your Enemies? and the joy of your hearts? when the inſtruments of death went over you, and about you, and ſcarce touch'd any of you that ſtood to the Cauſe, and did not flye away: when thouſands fell on each ſide of you and you were preſerved; doe not your hearts leape at the remembrance of it? did not the Lord appeare at that day glorious in holines, fearefull in praiſes, working wonders? did not the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines skip like Rams, and the little Hills like young ſheep at that day? did you not hew downe mighty Cedars at that day? did not God throw downe Mountaines, and fill up Vallies for you at that day? when hee brought you to
<hi>Plahiroth</hi> the very mouth of ſtraights, as he did the Iſraelites,
<hi>Exod.</hi> 14.2. when your Enemies thought you <hi>were entangled,</hi> and when they cryed, <hi>wee will perſue, we will overtake, we will devide the ſpoyle, our luſts ſhall bee ſatisfied, our Sword ſhall devoure</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.9. then did the Lord blow with his wind and the waters and waves of his wrath did overwhelme them, and they lay weltering in the red Sea of their owne blood: was not this a taken that your cauſe was good, and your Enemies bad? when thoſe of you that fled, were ſlaine, and thoſe that ſtood to it were preſerved? and thoſe of your Enemies that ſtood to it periſhed, and thoſe that fled eſcaped? how did GOD the Father protect you with his attributes? how did God the Sonne ſurround you (as it were) with his merits? and intrench you with his bloud? how did God the Holy Ghoſt cheer you with his comforts? working your hearts to a holy extaſie of joy, making you (like <hi>David,</hi> when he danced before the Arke) to forget your ſelves, and upon the diſcharge of your Muskets to cry out in holy and ſpirituall rapture, <hi>now for Ieſus Chriſt, now for the Goſpell, now lets ſee what prayer can dee</hi> &amp;c. when you were in the vallies of the ſhadow of death, yet did you not feare: and hath not God gon all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with you ever ſince? hath not God alwayes as before <hi>Ephraim Benjamin,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſtird up his ſtrength, and came and holpen you from time to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155919:6"/>time? as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath it,
80. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. alluding to theſe three Tribes which went immediately after the Arke, 2 <hi>Numb.</hi> 17. and 18. conſider therefore God the Fountaine of life, the great Preſerver of men, the upholder of all things by the word of his power is your Life-guard.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>you have a guard of Angells to attend you,</hi>
34. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7. the Angels of the Lord pitch their Tents round about them that feare him, and delivereth them, yea the Charets of God are twentie thouſand thouſands of Angells, and God is amongſt them for your ſecurity, 68. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 17. God ſhall give his Angells charge over you to keepe you in all your wayes, 91. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 11. little doe you know what Charets and Horſemen there are in the Mount readie to fight for you, when you come to battell, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.15, 16, 17. God hath legions of Angells to come to fight for you when you call upon him in the day of Battell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.53. tender is God over you to give his Angells for your guard, and his Miniſters a flame of fire round about you, can you miſcarry with ſuch a Life guard?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, conſider you <hi>have a guard of promiſes to attend you, where ever you goe,</hi> firſt <hi>the promiſes of military dexterity,</hi> that <hi>God will teach your hands to warre, and your fingers to fight and of protection</hi> that <hi>he will cover your heads in the day of Battell:</hi> 144. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 1. you have been looked upon as an unskilfull, meeke, puſillanimous Dove-like ſpirited people, and indeed ſo you are, but hath not God given you the skill; courage and valour as of mighty Princes, and made old Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, flie like hares and hide their heads from you? to their terrour and your wonder, that ever you ſhould have ſuch capacitie for ſuch ſervices ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to your genuine temper.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>you have the promiſes of</hi> proviſion and plentie, that though the Lions lack and ſuffer hunger, yet you that feare the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good for you, 34. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 10. in your march towards <hi>Canaan</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, (for that is your caſe) rather then you ſhall want, if you bee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and ingenuous in the cauſe purely for God, he will ſmite Rocks for you ſpread Tables in the Wilderneſſe, feed you with Angells food, the delicates of Heaven, the upper ſprings, <hi>dulcius è fonte,</hi> you ſhall have the very well of Life for your refreſhment.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>you have the promiſes of victory,</hi> that one ſhall chaſe a thouſand, and two ſhall put ten thouſand to flight, 32.
<hi>Deutro.</hi> 30 that if your Enemies come one way they ſhall flie from you ſeven waies, that no Sword nor Weapon that is framed againſt you ſhall proſper, 54. <hi>Eſay</hi> 17. that God will make his Church and People his battell Axe and Weapons of Warfare to breake in pieces the Nations of the Earth. 51. <hi>Ieremy</hi> 20, 21. &amp;c. and that God will make his people a new ſharp threſhing inſtrument, having teeth to thraſh the Mountaines, and to beate them ſmall, and to make the hills as chaffe
<hi>Eſay</hi> 41.15. that the Stone cut out without hands ſhall be that Kingdome, <hi>viz.</hi> of Chriſt, that ſhall never be deſtroyed, but ſhall deſtroy all Kingdomes, and people that ſhall riſe up againſt it, 2 <hi>Daniel</hi> 44.45. that God will binde Kings in chaines, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 149.8.9. and to execute upon them the judgement written, this honour have all his Saints. You may expect all theſe promiſes to be fulfilled, and the face of things doe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155919:6"/>looke as if they were now in fulfilling; and they muſt bee fulfilled in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that very cauſe which you have in hand; and why may we not believe but that even now the day of vengeance is in Gods hand, and the yeare of his redeemed is come?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>You have a guard of prayers round about you,</hi> millions of prayers like <hi>a Cloud of incenſe, Lev.</hi> 16.13. doe alwaies hang over you, and hover about you, the Prayers of many generations that went before you; you ſhall reap in joy what they have ſowen in Teares; little doe you know the many thouſands of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers night and day in your behalfe, when you happily have not opportunity, nor company, nor place of conveniency to poure out your hearts before the Lord. What are theſe great Victories and wonderfull deliverances vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed unto you, but the returne of prayers in your behalfe? that you ſo often proſper fighting in the valley is, becauſe ſo many <hi>Moſeſſes</hi> and <hi>Hurs</hi> are praying in the Mount.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, conſider <hi>you have a guard of providences</hi> for your defence, all tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all paſſages ſhall ſtill be loaded with your ſecurity; <hi>the Sunne is willing to ſtand ſtill in Gideon, and the Moone in the Valley of Dialon.</hi> The Sea will as gladly run backward, as forward for your deliverance. The Creatures delight to doe you ſervice: if God doth at any time bring you to ſtraights, it is for nothing, but to ſhew his power and love for your defence; if hee brings you to ſuch a poſture as that you can doe nothing but <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> it is onely to ſhew you and the whole World, <hi>the ſalvation of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you have a good firſt cauſe, and Secondly, a ſure life Guard you have, God, his Angells, his Promiſes; the Prayers of the Saints, and all providences for your incouragement.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Conſider <hi>the many infallible intimations, as ſo many predictions from heaven of your ſucceſſe;</hi> which are a thouſand times more promiſing then <hi>Elijahs</hi> Cloud, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi>
18.44. of great Raine, or an Evening red and lowring Skie, of a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding faire day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.3.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>the Spirit of Prayer and Supplication, is abundantly poured forth upon all the Saints in your behalfe.</hi> An infallible ſigne of your ſucceſſe. The Cloud of Incenſe <hi>Leviticus</hi> the
16.13 which are the prayers of the Saints, as will appeare by comparing that place, 141. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. is the Cloud of his preſence; and a little cloud of that nature, though but ſo big as <hi>Elijahs</hi> hand preſageth a plentifull ſhoure of heavenly bleſſings upon your heads. When God prepareth <hi>Daniels</hi> heart to pray, Sions captivity is at an end,
<hi>Dam.</hi> 9.4. Hee that prepareth the heart to pray, will cauſe his eare to heare, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17 ſuch prayers, and teares, ſuch ſighs and groanes, ſuch ſurrounding the Throne of grace, in publique, in private, in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, was never knowne ſince <hi>Adams</hi> daies, as are now in your behalfe. How many thouſand lies in the gap in your behalfe? every Jacob is become an Iſraell in your cauſe, can you thinke you ſhall miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry?</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>The Spirit of Faith and confidence of your ſucceſſe in this cauſe, is poured forth upon all the Saints,</hi> and this alſo is a certaine <hi>Omen</hi> of your proſperity: when God doth draw out the hearts of men to believe and to hope in his mercy, it is a ground of ſtrengthening their hearts, for then will he preſerve the faithfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155919:7"/>and plentifully reward the proud doer,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.23. the Lord ſhall help deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſave his people, becauſe they truſt in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.40. ſhould God enable men to hope, and truſt in him, and that upon Evangelicall and Divine grounds, and faile them how would he diſhonour his ſon? prejudice his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe? and diſcourage his people? nor certainly as the unbeliefe of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites was a provoking cauſe of Gods diſpleaſure againſt them, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of his people in this cauſe, is moſt acceptable in his ſight, and a certaine ſigne of good ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Conſider, <hi>God hath ſlirred up the heart of the State of the Kingdome,</hi> viz: <hi>the Parliament, and to lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke out and endeavour after a Reformation</hi> of all things that they can find diſpleaſing unto God, another moſt infallible and promiſing token of your ſucceſſe: we ſhall moſt commonly find, that humiliation, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Reformation in a people, have bin ſignes of mercy towards a people.</p>
               <p>It is true, we have an inſtance in Scripture of a moſt ſweet and glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in matters of Idolatry and prophaneſſe.
<hi>viz:</hi> the Reformation of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. and yet notwithſtanding the Lord turned not from the fearce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his great wrath wherewith he was angry againſt <hi>Iudah,</hi> &amp;c. 2
<hi>Kin.</hi> 23.26. but yet there was a great deale of difference between that Reformation and ours. For, firſt <hi>that Reformation was began by the King,</hi> and ſo he compelled the people by his Regall power hereunto; but
<hi>this Reformation is from the people,</hi> taking the firſt lawfull and beſt advantage from the conſtitution of the Kingdome to take up Armes in and under the Kings power and authority, ſetled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſequently by his command virtuall, though not perſonall, ſo that that Reformation of <hi>Ioſiab</hi> was by compulſion upon the people, whereunto they yeelded for feare: but this Reformation is even from the people out of love, though with the hazard even of the Kings diſpleaſure. Secondly, when GOD doth afflict a people from his former diſpleaſure; yet there is
<hi>commonly ſome new ſin which comes in as a mediation,</hi> and ſo provoketh <hi>God</hi> to remember the old ſcore: thus when Gods anger was ſtirred up againſt Iſraell, the Devill moved <hi>David</hi> to number the people, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. But heare we find no ſuch thing, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new Nationall ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>viz:</hi> any act of the State authorizing ſin, and the good Lord keep our Parliament from ſuch a thing; we ſee rather that it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ſinned that our enemies quarrell with us, but becauſe wee will not ſinne: our enemies quarrell againſt us, is not becauſe we have bin or are prophane in our lives, Idolatrous in our Worſhip, but becauſe we will not be ſo for if we would joyn with them in theſe abominations, we ſhould quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be at peace with them ſo that the very ſourſe and riſe of the wars, is the glory of God, and bleſſed be his Name that the cauſe is the Lords, and that wee can plead that before him, otherwiſe we might give our ſelves for loſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Affliction and judgement upon <hi>Iudah</hi> (the fruit of old diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt them for the blood of the Saints ſpilt in <hi>Manaſsah</hi> his daies) was <hi>the taking away of good</hi> Joſiah <hi>from them by</hi> Pharoah Neco <hi>King of Egypt</hi> who ſlew him at <hi>Megidde,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.29. ſo that God tooke <hi>away the Reformer</hi> from them, and ſo way is made for judgement upon them. But
<hi>now God increaſeth the number of Reformers,</hi> and hath ſo graciouſly opened the eyes of our VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155919:7"/>in matters offenſive unto GOD, as that they have done that which I am perſwaded they never purpoſed to doe.
<hi>viz:</hi> in the particulars, but onely to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the whole mind of
<hi>God</hi> as he ſhould reveale it unto them. And therefore notwithſtanding this inſtance, we have ſtill good hope from the Reformation begun: that God will own it, and the Temple ſhall be built though they build fighting, and that <hi>God</hi> will bring his people into
<hi>Canaan,</hi> though their enimies hearts are hardened, and perſue them with full purpoſes to deſtroy them. Yet their ruine will be both ſeaſonable and certaine.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Conſider <hi>The parties againſt whom you ſight,</hi> are a moſt <hi>Idolatrous, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, Delinquent, Prophane, Ignorant, or Hypocriticall</hi> Generation, take them where you will, from one degree to another, and you may fitly ranke them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome of thoſe unworthy denominations; for either they are Papiſts, and ſo
<hi>Idolatrous;</hi> Praelaticall, and ſo <hi>Superſtitious;</hi> Offendors of ſeverall kinds, and ſo <hi>Delinquents;</hi> Men of curſing deboiſt, lips and lives, and ſo <hi>Prophane;</hi> Men ſo incrediby beſotted, as to believe that the Goſpell, the Kingdome, the Lawes of the Land, the Liberty of the Subject, the Priviledges of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, the common peace and good of all is the onely Crowne, that theſe men fight for, and that you fight againſt theſe; which argues, the very ſenſible thickneſſe of <hi>Ignorance:</hi> or elſe laſtly, God and their own Conſciences can, and doe, and one day will evidence to their everlaſting ſhame; diſgrace, and torment, that they are as baſe diſſembling <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> as ever could be found among thoſe Scribes and Phariſees, againſt whom their are ſo many woes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. well, look upon your Enemies, they are the very worſt of ſinners, ſuch as we thought could ſcarce have bin conſiſtent with
<hi>Engliſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity. God hath ſeem'd to gather the very ſcum of all ſorts and qualities of men together, whether they be Men of high or low degree, and although their intention is to <hi>deſtroy Sion,</hi> 4.
<hi>Micha.</hi> 10. and though they ſay wee will now make an end of them at once and happily ſweare and curſe that not a Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head (as fooliſhly they call Gods people) ſhall be left in the Kingdom, yet <hi>Gods</hi> purpoſe may be the ſame meaſure unto them, as they intended unto us, 4.
<hi>Mich.</hi> 12. Namely, to thraſh them, and even to breake them in pieces. Your enemies are a people moſt ripe for judgement, they doe as it were invite the Sickle of Gods wrath to cut them downe. The ſinnes of the
<hi>Amorites</hi> are full, ſome of them are as it were rotten Ripe, and ſo have dropt downe before the time that God will ſhake them downe together.</p>
               <p>Thinke you that this Generation of Men ſhall bee your ruine? That the Stubble ſhall deſtroy the fire? Nay that hell ſhall ruine Heaven? and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill himſelfe ſhall deſtroy the workes of Chriſt, in revenge that Chriſt once came to deſtroy the works of the Devill? No let us caſt away ſuch ſurmiſings, and verily believe that the wickedneſſe of the wicked ſhall come to a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all end, and their owne deviſes will GOD make to fall upon their owne pates.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Conſider, <hi>God hath drawne the eyes of the while World, as it were upon his proceedings in this cauſe,</hi> and hath invited them to wait upon, and ſeriouſly to conſider the iſſue and upſhot of all; now when he cauſeth men to marke and conſider the upright; it is to ſhew <hi>that the end of theſe men is peace,</hi> 37. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37. he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155919:8"/>hath drawn the eyes of all the pious, and godly in the World, and this he rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth, except it be to ſhew them the ſalvation of God, 14. <hi>Exo.</hi> 13. Hee hath drawn the eyes of the wicked to looke upon the ſucceſſe of the quarrell, and this he rarely doth, except it be to let them know that God the Lord, is <hi>Iſraels</hi> God, and to make them confeſſe that <hi>there is a reward for the righteous</hi> &amp; that <hi>verily there is a God that judgeth the Earth, Pſal.</hi>
58.11. When the Lord did draw the eyes of the Iſraelites, and the Philiſtims together to try a ſingle combate, betweene <hi>Goliah</hi> and
<hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. though <hi>Goliah</hi> was for ſtrength, for greatneſſe and bigneſſe of perſon, for fearceneſſe, for weapons every way incomparable with <hi>David;</hi> yet this act of Gods providence in drawing men together to ſee the duell was to <hi>let all that Aſſembly know, that the Lord ſaveth not by Sword nor Speare, for the battell is the Lords, and that hee would give that uncircumciſed Philiſtim into</hi> Davids <hi>hands,</hi> ver. the 47. and ſo hath God done already, he hath made little ſtriplings, <hi>London</hi> Boyes as they call them, the ruine and downfall of the ſonnes of <hi>Anacke,</hi> and many
<hi>Guliahs</hi> who hath come out againſt them with blaſpheming tongues, and railing lips, ſhaking Locks. and ſparkling eyes, have fallen by their hands. Can you thinke that ever God ſhould call all men to looke and gaze, and wait for the ſucceſſe of this preſent controverſie, wherein his glory is every way ſo concern'd, and leave his people to the worſt? Did he ever doe ſuch a thing as this? Teſtifie againſt God, O thou doubting
<hi>Iſraelite,</hi> did ever God doe ſuch a thing as this? Would he not hereby diſcourage all men that come vnto him? And ſcare away all men that incline towards him? A thing which his Soule abhorres.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, Conſider <hi>how Gods name is every way ingaged in this quarrell;</hi> a pregnant <hi>omen</hi> of bleſſed ſucceſſe. It is true, we are a people (ſimply conſidered in our ſelves) fitted for judgement, having all, yea, and more provocations of Gods diſpleaſure againſt us, then ever any people that profeſſed the name of Chriſt, or could hope for mercy, barrenneſſe under ſo much meanes, abuſe of ſo much grace, ſlighting of ſo much Judgement, ſinning againſt ſo much experience, hath ſcarce beene found amongſt any that ever profeſſed the Name of Chriſt, whoſe preſent ruines doth teſtifie Gods ſore diſpleaſure againſt them for theſe things; and the good Lord give theſe thoughts of our owne abominations, a ſeaſonable, ſuitable, and pious Evangelicall operation upon our Spirits: but yet notwihſtanding though this might move God againſt us, yet this is not that which hath moved our Enemies againſt us; no, it is becauſe we are Gods people and Sheepe of his paſture, that theſe Wolves worry us: it is becauſe we deſire to repent and reforme, and will not joyne with them in all curſed waies of Idolatry and prophaneſſe; it is becauſe we would now worſhip God according to his will, and have no King in matters of our Conſciences but Jeſus Chriſt, that our enemies are ſo full of venome, fury, and madnes againſt us; and can we thinke that God will decline ſuch a cauſe as this? Did hee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doe ſuch a thing? Looke upon all the cauſes in the VVorld, was he ever more engaged, nay ſo fully and circumſtantially engaged in any as in this? how will his Name be blaſphemed amongſt them, if he ſhould doe thus? Would they not either ſay that your God is not able to help, and ſo mocke us and jeete us, and ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where are your Prayers, and your Faſtings? and your hope? and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155919:8"/>your faith? and Your God? or that God is the God of Papiſts, and Atheiſts; and Blaſphemers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not the God of <hi>Iſraell?</hi> and can his ſacred eares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſuch language as this? No ſurely, ſo long as we have <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> argument to plead, <hi>Lord what wilt thou doe with thy great name?</hi> Joſh. 7.9. ſurely the end ſhall be good, and Iſrael ſhall have the day.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Conſider, <hi>Your Enemies have begun to fall already,</hi> and this <hi>Hamans</hi> wife tooke as a ſad <hi>Omen</hi> of her Husbands ruine, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 6.13 and God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to deliver us, and this was alſo a good <hi>omen</hi> and bleſſed incouragement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.35, 36. and both theſe may be the like unto us. How have our enemies falne at <hi>Edge-hill?</hi> at
<hi>Wincheſter?</hi> at <hi>Chicheſter?</hi> at <hi>Gloceſter?</hi> at
<hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> at <hi>Stafford,</hi> at <hi>Caverſham</hi> neere
<hi>Reading,</hi> and in many other places, how hath he diſcovered their plots? infatuated their Councels? and blown up all their deſignes, <hi>given them all barren wombs, and dry breſts,</hi> and how hath God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo delivered us, and driven backe multitudes of our enemies by little handfuls, to the glory of his name, and the gnaſhing of the teeth of the Enemie, and their perpetuall ſhame and ſcorne; let this alſo give you plentifull incouragement of good ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>And therefore in the Eigth place, <hi>Conſider the conſequences of any loſse you ſhalt ſuſtaine in this Service;</hi> it is true, all experience witneſſeth that <hi>all things</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall providences <hi>falls out alike unto all men,</hi> and that no man can know either <hi>love or hatred: viz.</hi> of God, by any occurrences that <hi>are before them, Eccl.</hi> 9.1, 2. even a <hi>Ionathan,</hi> a <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> may fall in the day of Battell as well as others; but yet there are very many cordiall incouragements in reſpect of any conſequences whatſoever. Conſider, ſuppoſe you ſhould loſe a leg, an Arme, and Eye,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> have you not carried your lives in your hands, willing to ſurrender all up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and are you affraid leſt God ſhould take you at your word? You offer your life, and he takes but a Limbe, and is this your complaint? or doe you thinke that being diſmembred in Chriſt cauſe, he will not know you; is the badge of Honour (the markes of Chriſt your feare. Doe you thinke that that eye, or arme, or limbe which you looſe for Chriſt ſhall be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and not found at the day of your Reſurrection, but that it ſhall be a flaw in Gods Jewels even to all eternity? ſhall a Cup of
<hi>cold water</hi> in Chriſt cauſe, given, be remembred, and the blood of your veines, an arme an eye, a leg be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten? is doing for Chriſt ſo eſteemed, and ſuffering for Chriſt ſo flighted, ſuppoſe you looſe your lives in the cauſe, have you not offered them, and are you afraid leſt God ſhould accept of your offering? are you troubled leaſt you ſhould goe to God too ſoone, doe you feare your Crowne of glorie ſhould be too heavie, and make your head ake at that day? are you fearefull of being <hi>chiefe in the Kingdome of God?</hi> and of having part in the <hi>firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</hi> are you afraid you ſhall ſit too neere unto Jeſus Chriſt in Heaven? is his <hi>right hand</hi> in his glory your jealouſie? be not diſcouraged, your loſſes ſhall be gaine, and the degrees of the one ſhall anſwer the degrees of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God will be unto you our Wives, and Children like himſelfe in a way of recompence, for your
<hi>afflictions</hi> you ſhall have <hi>glory;</hi> for your <hi>light</hi> afflictions <hi>weight</hi> of glory, for your <hi>ſhort</hi> afflictions
<hi>eternity</hi> of glory, for your <hi>very light</hi> afflictions a
<hi>farre exceeding eternall</hi> weight of glory 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155919:9"/>let all theſe incouragements fill your hearts with a holy boldneſſe, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, Valour and Reſolution, to goe on, and to follow God fully in the mannaging of this Cauſe; and becauſe Dignitie doth alwayes imply Dutie: and Knowledge practice, take theſe few Directions for your more hopefull Succeſſe and comfortable proceeding in this Warfare.</p>
               <p>Firſt in the mannaging of this outward Warfare, <hi>do not forget your more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, inward and ſpirituall Warfare;</hi> it is a ſad and bitter thing to ſee how few Souldiers minde this thing, nay to ſee men (who before they entred into this Condition were ſeemingly, Religious Modeſt, Sober, Temperate men) ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly changed unto worſe, that few would believe they were the ſame men: what a ſad thing is it, to ſee mad men dance about the brincke and pit of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, without care or feare, alas! you are in danger of Death every moment, you know you walke in the Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey of the ſhadow thereof, if you have not Intereſt in Chriſt, your caſe is ſad, if you have, and yet a guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a looſe and careleſſe and negligent life and Converſation; alas! how can you expire, and breath out your ſoules into the hands of God with a cheerefull and comfortable Spirit? ſuppoſe you prove Victorious, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in all your deſignes (which the Lord grant) yet what advantage will you have by gaining without, and looſing within? what will the ſpoyles of your Enemies advantage you, when Sathan ſhall ſpoile your inward Treaſures? what is it to lead your Enemies into Captivitie; when your owne ſoules are lead into Spirituall bondage by the Divell himſelfe? what is it that you let out the bloud of your Enemies, when your vitall blood of inward ſtrength and Communion with God ſeemes to waſte? that you ſurround your Enemies, when your ſelves are ſurrounded with your ſpirituall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and therefore put on the whole Armour that you may be able to ſtand in the evill day, and having done all to ſtand ſtill, wreſtling with Principalities and power, the Rulers of the darkneſſe of this World, and ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high places, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11.12:</p>
               <p>Secondly, remember the adviſe of our Lord Jeſus in the 3. of
<hi>Luke</hi> 14. <hi>doe vi lence to no man, accuſe no man falſly, and be content with your wages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Doe violence to no man,</hi> nay, put no man in feare: Courage, and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtoutneſſe and tenderneſſe of Spirit, Reſolution and love, mingled and well tempered together makes a man meet to fight under Chriſts ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; if a man wants Courage his Enemies will not feare him; if meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, his owne Souldiers will not love him; had there been more Courage, ſtoutneſſe, and Reſolution both in Commanders and Souldiers, there had not beene ſuch flying away at <hi>Edge Hill;</hi> had there been more meekneſſe, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of Spirit and love, eſpecially in Commanders, happily there had not then ſo many of their owne Souldiers deſerted them, and got away from them; looke upon Jeſus Chriſt, who for his meekneſſe and love, to thoſe that fight under Him, is called a Lambe, a Dove &amp;c. and for Courage, ſtoutneſſe, and Reſolution is called the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah:</hi> a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardiſe milkſop in the day of Battell, and a paſſionate hot-ſpurre in his owne Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rters, doth ill become a Souldier of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cond Rule of Chriſt is, <hi>accuſe no man falſly,</hi> a thing as common as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155919:9"/>ſinnefull among Souldiers, to accuſe men of malignitie, that they may the more colourably plunder them; and ſo take away both mens Eſtates, and good name at once; Juſtice and Righteouſneſſe doth as well beſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me a Souldier as a Citizen; and the accompt of both before God ſhall be a like.</p>
               <p>The third Rule of Chriſt is, <hi>be content with your wages.</hi> As Covetouſnes doth alwayes ill become a Souldier: ſo eſpecially in this particular Cauſe and quarrell: for conſider, firſt
<hi>this Cauſe is for the exaltation of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and therefore thoſe who looke for comfort from the Cauſe, and Succeſſe therein, muſt aime at Him, and not to themſelves; if your aimes be pure for Him, He will ſee your pay good in due time.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you pretend the righteouſneſſe of the Cauſe, and not the benefit of the Warre that ſets you on worke, but is it ſo indeed? Come ſee my zeale for God ſaith <hi>Iehu:</hi> for the Throne ſaith God, and his owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>Iudas</hi> did ſeemingly forſake all and follow Chriſt, but the benefit of the bagg was his hand and hopes. When precious oyntment was ſpent upon Chriſt, he pleaded for the purſe under the notion of the poore, for his owne baſe ends under the colour of Charitie, are you for the Cauſe indeed? what, and not <hi>content with your Wages?</hi> yes, with all our hearts if wee could get it, ſaith the common Souldiers. How have you wanted it, by the deceit of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ſaith the common Voat; who like the unjuſt Steward in the Goſpell, which cozened his Maſter by his accompts; write upon the muſtering dayes a hundred for foureſcore, and foureſcore for fifty, who makes as little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of lying for money, as of telling the money they lied for. I give not the lye to Noble Souldiers; but to baſe diſſemblers; and to bee offended at theſe words is, (as the dipping of <hi>Iudas</hi> his finger in his Maſters diſh) a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſigne that that man will betray the Cauſe, if he can make a bargaine on it, though a Halter in the concluſion may determine there is nothing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by it. Well let thoſe (whoſe Conſciences ſpeakes plainely with <hi>Achan, Ioſhua</hi> 6. the 21. I tooke the Goodly Babiloniſh Garment, the two hundred ſhekells of Silver, and the wedge of Gold &amp;c.) let theſe I ſay who have troubled the <hi>Campe.</hi> the whole Kingdome, by deceiving them, both ſee the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations of this Delinquencie under theſe conſiderations.</p>
               <p>Firſt it is the moſt <hi>ſacrilegious Robberie</hi> that ever was committed, for it is moſt particularly againſt the very perſon of Chriſt, whoſe Cauſe chiefly it is, and how can you anſwer this at the great day?</p>
               <p>He that will rob Chriſt in a thing ſo deeply concerning his glory, would ſell Chriſt as <hi>Iudas</hi> did for the like profit. I could wiſh you would ſeriouſly remember the ſad example of <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Saphirah,</hi> ſmitten by God to death; for keeping back the accompt of his owne Eſtate; and his ſinne is aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from this conſideration, that he had lyed againſt the holy Ghoſt <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p>And if ſo? what will become of you, who keep back not your own but the Lords owne monies, being the Free-will offering of the Kingdome unto him. What doe you when you ſay I muſt have moneys for one hundred under me and returne it? when happily you have not about 60. or 70 to pay, and keepe up the reſt? but even lie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and rob Jeſus Chriſt, and to as great ſhame you ſhall one day acknowledge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155919:10"/>it, as ever did Thiefe make his Confeſſion at <hi>Tyburne;</hi> when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall bring to light your hidden baſeneſſe, lies, and diſſimulation; againe you rob the whole Kingdome, and are thereby as great oppreſſors, as ever Monopoliſts, or Patente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s have been, nay more in a great meaſure, you retard the worke of Chriſt, and are <hi>(horreſco referens)</hi> guilty of a great deale of blood ſhed in the Kingdome; I would you would ſeriouſly conſider of it. I have heard that ſome of you that have made a great profeſſion of zeale to the Cauſe, and of love unto Jeſus Chriſt, and that you applyed your ſelves unto the working the Warres out of theſe Principles; but now who more covetous than you? who more forward to comply with a ſinfull cuſtome of others in abuſing the State by baſe and ſelfeiſh dealings than you? which, (if you have true Principles of Piety) you could never doe without great paines ſinfully taken in ſtopping and in muzzeling the mouthes of your own Conſciences; which doth ſecretly vexe you within, if ſpirituall life be in you but as a graine of muſtard ſeed. Conſider, conſider, do you know how ſoone your breath may be wrung out of your Noſtrills, and will this comfort you in your dying agony? doth the wages of unrighteouſneſſe pleaſe you better than the love of Chriſt? let me be plaine, take heed of baſe diſſimulation; and hypocriſie. You would be thought to fight for the Cauſe, and for love unto Jeſus Chriſt, and this you ſay is your comfort, if you periſh you periſh in a good cauſe; and you are in Gods way, and you expect comfort; I would not trouble peace of conſcience; but why doe you trouble your owne peace. What, fight for Jeſus Chriſt; and rob Chriſt? doe you fight for Chriſt and ſteale away the Free-will offering of his people from Him? doe you fight for the Kingdome and deceive the Kingdome? what, and cannot endure to heare of any wayes of reforming abuſes; whereby the State hath been decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? well, know this, your greateſt gaines will be your loſſe, and your greateſt deceipt will be in your owne ſoules. Remember the Counſell of Jeſus Chriſt, doe violence to no man, accuſe no man falſely, and bee content with your wages. In the laſt place take heed of the common ſinnes of common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, of ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, looſeneſſe lightneſſe, vanity of ſpirit, labour for aſſurance of the love of God, and viſible Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt; minde your mortality, and let the thoughts of eternity poyſe your ſpirits, keep Faith and a good conſcience, get your hearts into a dying temper, and keep them therein, for you walke in the ſhadow of death, let God, and Heaven, and the deep things of the other World fill your thoughts, and in all your conditions ſtudie to be found in Chriſt, that having fought your good fight, finiſhed your courſe, and kept the Faith, your Warefare being accompliſhed, you may receive that Crowne of righteouſneſſe, which God the righteous Judge ſhall give unto you, and unto all thoſe that love his appearing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:155919:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
